the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
all right look at all these beautiful
cool kids in the room today uh welcome
to the stoa
everyone i'm peter limberg the steward
of the stoa stow is a place for us to
cohere and
dialogue about what matters most at the
nice edge of this very moment
and today we have ellie hayne and tarn
rogers johns
two insiders in the sense-making scene
who have seen the good bad and ugly in
this session
they will be talking about some of the
problems they've seen and
also uh presenting fresh new ideas
so how today is going to work it's a
60-minute session um
ellie and tony are going to speak for
about 30 minutes share their thoughts
and then we're going to pivot the q a if
you have any questions throw your
question in the chat box i'll call on
you
mute yourself ask your question um if
you want me to read on your behalf this
will go on youtube
i just indicate that uh and that being
said
i will take turn and ellie in
boom you're up
i am
hi everyone hello um thanks fear for
inviting for hosting
we're very happy to be here so
yeah should we do a short intro a short
intro yeah should we
start sharing the screen maybe um yeah
okay um
can i about we need to stop the video
oops
yeah one moment
sorry
okay all right
what is it
oh no oh no i don't know how to start
technical difficulty anyway i'll we'll
just start with the interest rates
yeah um so my name is turn as peter said
and uh i um until recently i was working
as editor of emerge which some of you
might be familiar with through the
emerge podcast
which is kind of loosely associated with
us and uh
yeah and that's what i've been doing and
i think my entrance into this
into this world was kind of atypical in
that
i had didn't really know anything about
it until i had
was paid to learn about it and and
uh yeah which is definitely typical in
that i think a lot of people
come into this scene because they're
working in jobs where they're being
paid to do something that doesn't
inspire them and
so i had a real quick learning uh curve
when i first started working at emerge
and previously to that i think i i came
from this background that was quite um
typical of someone in my generation it
was quite
post-modern and was very concerned with
being woke
and kind of and then when i arrived in
the scene i um
i kind of that was all deconstructed and
and i saw i think i went on a journey
that was quite similar to what we need
people to go on or we need a group of
people to go on
in order to kind of make the change we
want to see in the world um
kind of real um and so yeah
yeah cool um my journey
towards my modernities and game b was
quite different
but probably more similar to most of the
people here so i
i was actually a law student and was
like fully in the
game a hustle um
and then i discovered that was really
miserable so i just kind of like fell
down the internet rabbit hole
um the twitter ready podcasts
um and got sucked into it
and i think i had an experience that
many people can relate to
that essentially is at the fir at first
you're just so fascinated because you
find these people that look at the world
through
the similar lenses that you had but um
more meta
and they're seeing the same problems
that you do and they feel similar than
than you do
um and this generates a lot of initial
excitement
and then when you find the sense of
community when you realize that this is
just like not only a few people
that's um
i think like a scene that's getting
together
but then i i also started working
at emerge that's how tarn and i met in
berlin where we are right now
um but then during this journey
i also saw some of the problems and i
got some
some of the disillusionment that i see
that
people are also bringing up and that's
what we want to talk about today but
it's very important to say that
we we want to address these from the
sense
that we are in the same team like even
though we're criticizing the only reason
why we're criticizing is because we want
to see this movement and we if we can
call it this way
reach its maximum potential
so yeah everything coming from a place
of love
but we still need to talk it's important
yeah so yeah okay um what did we do for
these presentations
tarn um yeah we had a problem yeah so we
actually spent quite a lot of time
um i mean so coming back to um
to who we are i when i first met ellie
it was the first time i'd
really had the opportunity to bounce you
know i came from this kind of
um this background of a feminist theory
that was really my
my thing when i was at uni i was very
from a very feminist perspective
and then i arrived in the scene which
was kind of really
critiquing the um the culture the kind
of culture was and i could see
how needed that was but i wasn't able to
kind of marry these two perspectives
until i met ellie and it was the first
time i'd ever really been able to say
okay uh you know i get that what's going
on in feminism is problematic right now
but also does that mean that
the only people that we listen to now
are men
um yeah so it was kind of this was the
first time i'd ever really been able to
bounce
ideas off someone and have them
reflected back at me and
i think because we come from a similar
subculture
yeah exactly yeah we were able to bond
in
in this seeing someone that looks like
you and not just for
representation issues like that's not
the main
problem that we're trying to address but
feeling that you're seeing in your
experience and that you're able to
to talk with someone that like really
understands where you're coming from
especially
not just being a woman but being young
and
in this case like also european uh from
a movement that tends to be like quite
u.s centric
um yeah we also wanted to say at the
beginning we kind of like skipped this
part
but oh yeah yeah yeah that what happened
is that we had this like presentation
at dawn at the beginning and then we
realized that we were
falling into the same problem that we
were trying to criticize essentially
that we want to bring up some problems
um but that a lot of people are
already acknowledging and we were not
bringing like something truly fresh
so then we just decided to go a bit on a
different way and that's why we decided
to
do the memes um for this presentation
because i feel like they are very
good new ways of communicating and some
of the
problems that we want to tackle in the
end and what means oh hi
memes because they're funny and i love
um and we need more humor totally like
that's
that's for one but also because i feel
that memes are truly
the new form of communication of the
21st century
they are so powerful they have so much
cultural information ingrained in it
and because they have this like visual
aid
but also with text you have the an
emotional reaction that you just see
with the with the person and this is
what creates the connection to the
embody part of the conversation that we
sometimes miss
or or say that's lacking when you see
you know you see like
pablo escobar like he's like feeling
like really sad and that's essentially
how i felt this morning like wow
i didn't know this conversation and if i
call the script and it's i feel like
it's worthless or
saying when you feel like woody here and
you have
what do you write like
yeah and this is like the sense making
people trying to like
map for us all these new pathways to the
new planetary civilization
and everything sounds so amazing it's so
poetic and of course like i'm drawn to
it like that's
why i i fell into it in the first place
but at the same time we're just like
woody
like we're young we still need to make
money yeah
um how how do we survive um it doesn't
it it
uh richard thought i said in a star
conversation recently
kind of like it can be intellectual junk
food like it feels
it feels really good and you're like wow
that's
it and then when you leave you're kind
of like oh okay what do i what do i
do now but yeah exactly especially and
that's something that
we see brought up tony were saying that
when you were editor you would
get quite often emails from young people
saying that what is this you know i want
to be part of this
and many times ellie and i have had the
experience of being in groups of friends
where we start talking and everyone's
just quiet because they're like this is
so interesting this is so different and
i need
i i'm this people are so hungry for this
yeah i have several friends that have
you know kind of attempted to to kind of
you know intelligent
intelligent people who engage try and
engage and then i yeah i don't
i don't really you know they can't
follow me and also this sense
of we're mapping out how the world
ideally would look like if we're lucky
in say like 30 years but we're still in
today we're still like
in the system the gaming system or
however you want to call it and what is
the next step and for me that was
something that
as someone who got into these
um thinking from when i was quite young
like 20 or 21
and i still had my whole career ahead of
me i was like wow so what am i supposed
to do like do i need to play along and
that
generated a lot of anxiety for me this
way
but um yeah yeah and then we're
we're just gonna quickly go through the
problems but then talk about the
solutions we just have them
down here then
yeah there's the fact that these
conversations
seem to be a lot a one-way conversations
between
the heroes the sense makers the chief um
yeah sense makers and then everyone else
that we were so eagerly
um following them and created this kind
of like personality called which is fine
like
i get it because they do have very
insightful things to say
but if we're talking sense making and
sense making is something that we're
doing
collectively and every person is kind of
a sensor
and that has some noise and some signal
in in in the jargon we need as many
sensors as we can in order to have the
best since making possible in order to
like have the most complete
picture of reality but then again what
time was saying
we fell into this same we felt that we
perhaps transcended postmodernism
but where were the women where are the
different people
and it's not just about women
yeah it's not it's not coming at it from
this perspective of
identity politics and it's different
ways of thinking different ways of
constructing meaning different ways of
talking and even interacting
and we are we're aware that we we talk
in a very different way
than people sometimes come on this
podcast
and it's just about being able to then
arrive in these conversations and
and and kind of find the the symbiosis
find the space in between
in order to come up with kind of
solutions that we need to fix the
problems that we're all facing
exactly and different ways of showing up
it's not just enough to have
you know the very diverse picture but
just do you come up with
like your vulnerability that you come up
with humor do you come
with you know a more like less
intellectual way of speaking but that's
still very
embodied and resonating with a lot of
people like which essentially we all
have a framework that we've constructed
and
that we feel is very powerful which are
all the different ways
all the different tools that we can make
sure this
framework is worldview gets to the most
people as possible
um so yeah yeah so that's
one part yeah i think that's uh-huh yeah
yeah you didn't move yeah
okay then a big part of culture
culture change i mean what do we mean
when we talk about culture change
um well ellie was bringing up with the
with the means
with the memes and this is why we
decided to kind of meme this entire
conversation because
as this meme says we could speak about
this for like 10 minutes and probably
give you the same
intellectual understanding of what we're
saying as just looking at this meme
against you
exactly um and this is why we need to
kind of find
these ways of communicating these ideas
out
yeah in essence these me my feeling
represents
what the whole conversation could be
like is culture change or is it just
like an hour-long podcast conversation
um
it's very important to have the theory
and to have the sense making in a way
that's what
kind of like furnishes your brain i feel
but we need to distinguish between
the kind of knowledge that is um let's
say classificatory
versus a kind of knowledge that is
generative that really creates uh can
kind of change
culture chains and i feel like there is
was um a lot of resistance towards
making things popular making things
mainstream and i get that yeah sometimes
when
a product that's very pure which is the
mainstream it can get corrupted
but we need to find the ways of playing
with the system in order to reach
um all the people that we want to reach
and to make this a truly a
global movement you were saying this
thing about climate change before when
we're talking
um yes um
i was saying that i get the sense i mean
we live in this kind of we
live in a culture where there's a lot of
fragmented
movements um and when last year when
the kind of extinction rebellion stuff
kicked off there was this kind of sense
of
oh finally there's a kind of global
movement that we can all get behind
and this is this has the same potential
i mean obviously
things have evolved since that um
original kind of
fervor behind um extinction rebellion
but
i think this this has the potential to
have the same kind of uniting
yeah united potential and in a time
where
it's like where the time right now feels
extremely ripe for these kinds of ideas
we're saying before that when corona
came this fight
it is objectively quite bad and our
lifestyle gets definitely negatively
impacted
it also felt like a kind of relationship
yeah it was a really great opportunity
opening up
a lot of excitement because it kind of
felt like we've been talking about
systemic breakdown and
collapsed for a while and it was finally
like other people were starting to kind
of
feel it as well and it was kind of
permeating our daily
our daily lives and so yeah the overton
window is open and it's and it's time
it it's a good time to really be
thinking about how
to spread these ideas further exactly
and it felt
like it became more obvious that all the
previous pathways that had been
tried and tested were not working
anymore so it was a time where people
it's a time where it feels that everyone
collectively is like way more open to
being truly radical
and brave and experimental in how we're
bringing about change
um so yeah that's how we should approach
also the issue of culture change i hear
i make
yeah a bit of the differentiation
between the
system builders so those are like the
people who are actually building
say the economic educational um
political systems that we're ingraining
versus the culture changes these are the
people that create the imaginary
culture in general and this is more in
the artistic creative domain and how do
we
collaborate between these people
and of course there's like essays are
very important these are part of theory
but which new ways of bringing this like
theory down to the masses can we
um yeah but this is very hard
if all your theory and all of our
message is just completely wrapped in
jargon in group jargon
yeah um yeah we had
we've had an interesting experience with
this the past weeks because we're
scripting a podcast
uh series and so what we're trying to do
is take
the theory that we that we've
we know we've come across and um bring
it down
to you know literally this physical act
of kind of bringing it down to real
world
real world examples real um real
cultural examples
um and then we would get like wrapped
into these like mine spins because we
were like
is that like is that what it is i don't
like
yeah and it was it's this kind of you
really realize through the process of
trying to make something
tangible how much
how much is implicit um in a lot of uh
very conceptual
thinking and sometimes how little you
actually know
sometimes it felt or you may know that
you need to like really
bring it out sometimes it felt like
trying to pin down a dream
when you use jargon where you use like
these like highly complex phrases
it's just like oh yeah and of course it
resonates it's beautiful
right but then when you're trying to pin
it down to essentially like what it
means
it's like trying to remember a dream
that you like dreamt last night it's so
hard
and so that's why even though sometimes
jargon makes us sound extremely smart
um the smartest way or like how we
actually sound smarter
is when we're just being crisp and clear
in what you want what we want to do
especially if we're talking about
um yeah creating things from the ground
up but we were seeing that when we were
doing business proposals
that it was so easy to get caught up
into the rhetoric but it was really hard
to actually
say what we wanted to do well jargon
serves
purposefully because it can it's
bringing um
it is kind of naming things that maybe
don't already exist
and and kind of giving them making them
embodied
creating a new concept for them like no
idea that yeah and also it can be an
in-group identifier so you know
who vibes with you who's reading the
same things as you
listen to the same podcast and in a
really really complex world
um it's it's even more important because
we live in this such
scattered information apology where you
know it's
you kind of it's kind of instinctive to
want to know who your tribe is
um yet you know it's not
it's not necessarily going to do the
purpose of a kind of wide scale culture
change that
we're talking about um yeah and about 10
minutes so
oh we've got 10 minutes okay
all right so this is just yeah another
illustration
of of like how you can speak
in turkey yeah and yeah
yeah okay
so yeah enough we've done
this is a description of this this is
the description of the session
i think exactly it's important that
jargon yeah
serves this like community purpose that
is not
completely um disposable
yeah we had a lot of fun writing this
because it was actually fun writing in
the jargon and we understood it all so
we were kind of like we were like yeah
and then we were like no no
this is this is supposed to be funny
because we were kind of also kind of
into it
yeah um but if
i was to say like something really good
that this team has created in the first
place is that it has
created a sense of community of a lot of
people that felt
alone before they did really like who
are the people that see the world
through the same lenses as we do and i
felt like that that's what i was drawn
to in the first place and just having
this
feeling that you're not alone that
there's more people like you they're not
the only weirdo out there
and it's extremely positive and then i
can understand how this
reinforces the use of jargon because
it's this like signifier like cultural
signifier
that we belong we're in the same tribe
um but ultimately
it comes back to is about conditions
it's exactly it just creates the same
conditions so
yeah we just wanted to analyze it to
science um
next okay but enough sense making and
criticizing then we will just fall into
the same trap we're
so good at analyzing but not that good
at solution creation and we're running
out of time
not just like in the session but also
like in broader context scale like we
are running out of time guys
for so we need to think of solutions we
are in the solutions department
um this is this could be i mean we had a
brief conversation with peter before
this is
this is a much bigger conversation than
what we're able to cover in this
in this session and we have a lot of
ideas um but this is just kind of a
taster
yeah and we're gonna focus on the
solutions regarding
the communication and rather
ex yeah communication of of the
sense making scene and how do we make
these like penetrate the mainstream
because that's what we focused in
we are communicators and yeah we're
working on immersed that's how we met
but we recognize that this is only part
of the solution we also need a lot of
people like people on the ground system
builders
that are actually um building the
real systems that will make the world
that want to live
with happen but regards to
communications as we're
saying um
memes memes new things going back to the
same thing we decided to do this
presentation
um with memes in a way to illustrate the
point that a lot of the things that we
say can't just be um
explained in like a very short image but
the power of memes
is not just that like if we if we
analyze the current culture war
that we're at um the polarization the
political prioritization
this war was not fought with theory it
was fought with
memes and especially like how the
outright gain so much dominance
it gained dominance through like these
extremely transgressive extremely
provocative
um memes that started in in forums like
h and 4chan and then spread
like widely and what this culture always
made fun of was that the left couldn't
meet
and then i say if the left hand mean
like we don't even try
like not only we don't try but we just
think that
it's or at least what i've seen from the
in the scene it's like
it's enormities that like need to get
out to us like they need to like step up
their complexity
it's an opinion i've come across a lot
is that people
don't people shouldn't read what they
want to read they need to read
this and they this is usually like a 4 4
000 word essay um and
i find it it's been very difficult to
communicate the people
that's just it doesn't work like that
yeah and
then in the end even though if that's
the ideal solution we need to be aware
that we
don't we're not in a terrain where we
can like choose the ideal and we need to
play with culture and if that means
being a bit less pure but it works in
regards to the impact
then we need to recognize that at some
point we need to have some metrics and
we need to
see like yeah is it are we only in the
business of like being purist and like
making the most sophisticated
theory and we might be but then we need
to recognize that and
at least like not putting our shoulders
and metal off like oh no here we're
no system changers yeah um and
yeah how the how do like the metamodern
people mean
that would be like super interesting and
then another part
um of culture change is influencers
yeah okay about influencers
um i mean even the the the term
influencer
within me brings up a lot of judgment
it's strange it's good for me too
yeah because it's it's um it's people
who are kind of playing the system
extremely egotistical
and and sort of self-absorbed and that
is a lot of influence or culture
and i think this uh this meme really
sums up
the different levels that you can think
about um influences yeah
i feel like like a lot of people even
maybe perhaps like the influencers
themselves like
hate easter because we have this
association of like influencers being
the basic [ __ ] and like that's
yeah the most basic way of thinking
about them but then you just realize
like the system that they're ingrained
in and then there's like
influencers as a food soldier stuff like
capitalism it's not about them it's just
the environment
yeah and then recognizing as you say
it's that it's a
viable it's it's you know it's um
i think they did they did a study on
teenagers and it used to be that
they wanted to be doctors and they
wanted children they wanted to be
firemen
and now they say they want to be
influencers you know this is this is
kind of seen as a viable career choice
for young people and that is the culture
that we're living in um
and so how do we work instead of just
critiquing this and
and kind of piling judgment on it how do
we work with that system
um yeah and not only that it
feels so in a way because
you know the times that we're living in
and like how just extremely bad the
economy is for young people
speaking firsthand is
it feels like the only like viable
options that you have is like extreme
hustle
it can be extreme hustle in the startup
way that's like the more
like techy broadway or extreme hassle in
the pimp out your personality kind of
way and just
yeah like it really is what it is um
and so i can like definitely understand
how like toxic disease but
if if you read um
like through the current situation it
really feels
you know if like all the systems are
clumping well at least i have myself to
support if i'm likable or not then i
have that
and it's not that i'm not saying that
we're like trying to support this
culture but
the next step would be that influencers
in a way they
yeah yeah they're just like the
archetypal representations
of what we value in a system so right
now of course the young
influencers that we have and like the
people that we have there the heroes
they are the ones that like represent
what we think of as elite in a culture
and of course there's just like not one
um
monoculture we live in a globalized
society like hyper society that we have
a lot of subcultures
and the difference influencers represent
um the different values that these
subcultures have
but how do we play um with the system
how do we play with the senses and not
against it and in this way creating
these like new
representations truly embodied because
that's what influencers are like
embodied values
and that society of health so like how
would this representation look like
yeah and i think this is something that
we've seen a bit of in the modern scene
with
hansi kind of um
uh alter ego and i think that was kind
of
an awareness of the power of kind of
archetypal um
personality exactly and yeah with hands
it's like super intellectual but it
could be even
something like very subtle but it just
transpires
um the values or like the even like
sensibilities that we're talking about
in a very subtle way
but the thing about subtlety and showing
something rather than
explicitly telling and explicitly
telling the theory
is because when you get it then you're
just like connecting with
through emotion and that's when it
becomes like directly embodied
even though it means that maybe you
consciously rationally
are not even aware of what you're um
talking about
so yeah i think that's that's it yeah
and that's
perfect timing yeah oh yeah yeah well
just
exactly and how do we collaborate you
know the creatives with the system
builders the theories with the
hipsters essentially people with
cultural capital
and all this stuff and yeah thank you
thank you daddy
thank you thank you peter for the
yeah for giving us your space uh to to
test these ideas and
exactly interested to the community and
able to yeah
come in with our full selves yeah okay
cool
um so if uh if you have any questions
start throwing in the chat i'll call you
in a moment
but like to double click on that kind of
the stoic daddy holy [ __ ]
thing that we were joking up before and
related to i'll i'll stop for you uh
yeah stop description
yeah uh we were talking about kind of
like vibe
like how vibe is different from content
um and you can kind of say the same
thing propositionally but you can say
like with a different vibe it's going to
resonate with people more
um and like for example like the whole
game b scene
like i can interface with their
propositions i i like them i learn a lot
but i just don't
buy that that that scene it's just like
it feels kind of icky a lot of fanboying
fangirling going on there
or with like the stoicism movement
there's only like one stoic in the stone
that's me
and i don't really vibe with the modern
stoic movement it just feels
disembodied and so the store has
cultivated its own
vibe and a lot of people are vibing with
it but everyone's gonna vibe with it
right so this like this idea that we can
have a vibe diversity
and that's okay and i think that's
that's what you're gesturing at so i was
wondering if you can
maybe speak on this like mono vibing
that's occurring in the scene versus
like cultivating a vibe diversity
yeah i really like looking at it through
the
permaculture principle of diversity and
and how and if you have a monoculture
for if you have a monoculture of people
is you get a sense of safety and
community but
you're not going to get the soil the
rich soil that you need to
to grow rich solutions
and i think if you have a kind of strong
different ecosystem of thought than you
will then you will create richer soil
and in different vibes and i like that
system of vines yeah
biodiversity is great and i think the
the problem with
this and the reason why it's it's
difficult is that it
it creates conflict and and it means
that you have to be comfortable with
being uncomfortable in a way that maybe
you you know because we talk about being
comfortable with being uncomfortable a
lot in in this
scene but in a different way in a
different way that
you can't anticipate yet and it's just
it's a lot more difficult
to have a diversity of vibes and still
you know disarm your judgment and disarm
your
your superiority complex in your library
yeah yeah the
um do you have any anything about on
that early
well yeah especially the fact that
different
bikes resonate with different people and
that abide
um
how to say um
each vibe like serves a different kind
of purpose
and there's no like better vibes and
like bad vibes in here like the analogy
that comes to my head
is when people used to criticize um
techno like techno music and electronic
music
saying that oh this is not good music
this is just sound
and then like this dj the answer that he
he came up with was like the people that
criticized this they don't understand
the context in which is meant to be
enjoyed
and so i think that this yeah
it's because yeah of course like you're
not supposed to like use a new
technology headphones and like in your
room when you're trying to relax as you
would it's like classical music
or like normal speaker and i think that
that is the same
with vibes like each bag
works in a certain context and like
serves a specific purpose and it's not
about like which fight
is that's better like which way is not
better is that we need
to make space and that's what i refer to
like
metamodernism gaming distance making is
being a framework
and that framework like the purpose that
it should serve is to
open up for all these different kinds of
apps it's just kind of like the os
that you have in body and then you come
up as your authentic self with
it but it's just it's not a way of it's
not a personality
right and we've kind of associated
um the sense making scene with a type of
personality but that's just because the
first people that came there like had
these
and also because then this creates an
attractor that it feels that you can
only be part of this if you have this
personality
but that's just it's completely [ __ ]
like it's just not true and that's not
the
way that it can work the best the way
that it can work the best this is just
the os
you have it within you that's like the
bill that you have and then you create
your you just show up as your authentic
self with the bite that you resonate
most and then you find the others and
you
pollinate in that way so
yeah yeah i like that a lot um and
what's coming to mind is
is what we were talking about before we
let people in about embodiment and then
that
session high pitch with bonita nora rhea
um and how when i was there i just
felt embodied listening to them they
were like six ladies talking and that
was it
i just felt so embodied but i also the
content was rich as well
and then uh so there's like an
embodiment vibe there which i'm curious
to get
your thoughts on and then right after
that uh greg henriquez zack stein and
jordan hall had a session
it was like you know escape velocity
meta like all this like you know
galaxy brain stuff and it was good but
it was a totally different vibe
um and i do think it's a wrong move to
kind of shame that that that vibe
because that's an onboarding point for a
lot of people as well
and so i'm curious uh what you think
about this like an embodiment vibe and
maybe how it relates to
women and femininity uh and how it could
interface with this kind of
more meta uh disembodied vibe
well um
this is something that i've coming
personally and having worked
in this and i i feel like i'm
quite a feminine essence person in order
to be able to kind of intellectually
um to speak in an intellectual way or to
speak in this meta level i have to have
felt a heart connection and an emotional
connection first and i really struggle
in these
environments where um where the pressure
is just to
kind of present and kind of put your put
your ideas out there and kind of
and be um be one of the heroes
um and i i don't i need to be embodied
in order to
in order to access it and i think that's
um
something that i've experienced and it
was lacking and
and yeah exactly like this feeling of
being embodied
that i also got from the from the
conversation with nora
and juanita and it's something that
helps people to feel grounded and
comfortable and um
yeah absolutely and also sometimes when
i see these like hyper intellectual
conversations
for me it's funny because i get the
feeling that the people
that talk they don't think that they
don't seem disconnected
right either like i i've seen very
intellectual people
in real life and online but yeah and
they do come across as disconnected but
like
fortunately like not the people like
jordan or like
zac stein at least i don't yeah or
danish mike burger like i don't know
them personally but the feeling that i
have from them is that
they are integrated and embodied people
so then like how is it that we've
created this
environment that just brings out these
parts of themselves
um but then on the other side on the
embodied conversation the funny thing
about embodied conversation or um
embodied living of this is that
sometimes you don't even need the
content reach
this is something that i think joe was
here
joe edelman from um human systems you're
here hi
um and he's a really good friend of mine
and we were
when we hang out we talk a lot um
or at least at the beginning we did of
how what we do is not
talking about game b but really playing
game b and even though we can go like
super intellectual sometimes our hanging
out we're just playing games and we're
just being silly and being funny
but all the things that we're doing like
they're just really strongly
um having themselves all the values that
we talked about
it just manifested and sometimes like
the intellectual content of it is zero
and it's not because we can't do it
but it's just because there reaches a
point where you don't need to anymore
when you've gone through like all these
ideas and like you you just get it
the appeal and the alert of like all
this meta talk
it's just like yeah i've i had to peel
you know um so
yeah but this is not to say that the
content of it is not rich because it's
obviously it's wow
right so uh we'll pivot to the chat
let's ask one quick question um and i i
do agree that like guys like daniel
smartburg or zack stein are very
embodied but there's something about the
broadcast
mode that creates a certain energy
especially when you're not an epistemic
peer with someone
um but like so what is uh the vibe
that you two are bringing uh and
especially with your project that you
have going on in berlin that you're
going to launch soon yeah
um what is our vibe
what is our vibe um
it definitely it's it's more
playful young and cheeky and rare
like irreverent one of the things that i
that i found was that
um and i'm just gonna like be now
completely like honest in myself here
yeah um that we had like so much like
wholesome
earnest like boy scout energy voice
garbage
boy scout energy and like we love the
boy scouts like they're
you know super sweet like the
hufflepuffs
but we need more archetypes like right
that's what creates like richness of
soils
um so what is the you know like
mean girl like you know the bad witch
like sexy kind of like bad boy
because there's like a lot of appeal in
that in a way like going jordan peterson
see
um it's you know if you cannot take if
you're like just too good that people
cannot be afraid of you
then you cannot you know if you people
don't feel like you can stand up for
yourself like you cannot stand up for
others
um battles and that's like the sexiness
and the appeal that of the
bad boy um archetype but
also um there's this element of being
like slightly provocative and
transgressive
that has that's what i was trying to do
with the memes i know that some of them
like can feel a bit triggering for some
people
but for me that is something that i want
to play with and like play with the
edges
and i feel it's very true to the metal
modern spirits
of having extremely good intentions
because i believe that everyone that's
here
um do have really pro-social
intentions and we want to create like a
radically better world you know can we
make a
utopian like yes let's do it but if
we're just only coming with this energy
it feels sometimes naive or kind of
like disconnecting from people who are
like not that into it so then you need
to add a bit of
i say evil for spice you know like a bit
of like a slithering vines and that's
when it creates like
much more complexity like this duality
comes and it's just i feel it's
a much more attractive product but in
the end
everyone should just be their authentic
self and like have their authentic vibe
even though authenticity can
well yeah and then and within and within
you know within the project they'll be
their own mini vibes as well
so yeah yeah and we have a similar buy
but we're not even like the same right
no no yeah i mean i don't know
yeah um
but yeah i mean we could go only cool
um so let's uh pivot to the chats now
uh right now heaven
yeah so um peter that discussion that
you just were having uh kind of
prefigured and touched on some of the
elements of my question but i'm just
going to go ahead and read it and let
you take it wherever you want um
so my question is a problem with the
sense making scene which i have noticed
and which
you also seem to have gestured at in
your presentation is that the
major players seem to generally conceive
of or at least to like transmit a sense
of
sense making as a primarily intellectual
activity
you know there's a heavy focus on
epistemology and similar framings
and to me this seems to allied the deep
mutually supporting and interdependent
relationship between skillful ways of
relating to our embodiment
to our emotional experiences and to our
intellectual capacities so
lots of people in the sense making seem
seen seem to have their own practices
and ways of skillfully relating to these
aspects of human experience but they
seem to under
emphasize the skills of embodiment and
for lack of a more precise term a sort
of
tantrically vibed way of skillfully
engaging with one's emotions
relative to the importance of those
things for good sense making and so i'm
curious to hear your thoughts regarding
the ways
in which the sense making scene could
better emphasize the development of the
whole human which seems to me to be
necessary for truly excellent sense
making and choice-making
great question
the questions how can the sense making
seem better integrate an awareness or
integrate a kind of um awareness of the
importance of an emotional
and embodied way of making sense
um well yeah by doing exactly that
by integrating it and having these kind
of conversations that we're having now
um
and like you say it's spoken about it
it's something that's mentioned but it's
i mean how do we
um how do we create spaces in which
people can physically have that
experience rather than just speaking
about it and this is something that we
tried to do with the emerge gatherings
was to create these spaces where people
could
could kind of have these embodied
experiences but um you know
it it yeah it had its uh i
yeah i feel like this is essentially a
social design
problem um because we're talking about
how
we carry these conversations and how we
engage in these conversations and a
conversation
even though um we're so used to them
that we don't see it
has a specific design to it and the
design is that i talk you listen to me
and if this is like a conversation then
that
i'm the one that's talking and there's
certain like social norms
of what is it accepted to say and like
not accepted to say
and how you should show up and how you
should not show up and
this is like the invisible code of
conversations
so i feel like here the crucial um
like the crucial point that we should be
trying to look at in order to like shift
these conversations to a more
um full human embodied uh way of of
being um would be to look at this code
and then experiment like create
conversational games
so in this conversational game we're
gonna try to and
pin down the values that we want um
to try to experiment in that in in that
like little conversation so
in this conversation we're going to try
to talk intellectually but
with vulnerability and then with a
social designer maybe this is something
that we could do in the next
um social design club at the store
redesigning um the sense making
conversations but
it is actually a design problem that we
need to experiment
we need to like pin down which are the
values that we want to create and then
see see which are the methods that work
best um
and this is probably like not a
conversation that we should have
but like a doing a design session
yeah i love that and like the keys for
that
yeah i like that the idea of making it
playful too you know like
that with the focus on these redesigning
these sense making conversations um so
if you have any statements to that you'd
like to say and just i will call on you
as well he doesn't have to be a question
uh cheryl you had a thought i think
would be
good to share yeah i'm happy to share
i love this session um what you were
describing about
your vibe being very irreverent and
playful i think i just
i found it very immediately disarming
about
i would say a scene that i've been
curious about and kind of
adjacently attending a lot of talks
around
but i also haven't been feeling quite
the vibe of it
even though i think a lot of the content
resonates
and just seeing the two of you show up
and kind of like
be badass with your memes i think made
it feel frankly a lot more accessible
to me um so yeah i think there is like
this
real power to being able to
i think use humor especially to disarm
so thanks for that i just wanted to
say we need more of you
thank you so much that's yeah that's
really great to hear
probably that would have been me yeah
any of these years back yeah so lively
feeling
manuel you had a similar comment
yes thank you ladies forgive my photo
i'm not video friendly right now um
i feel so much resonance with you yes we
need more of you
and i am one of you um the high
intellect was a part of my onboarding
via jordan hall
and i i do appreciate all the
deliciousness
you know solar masculinity and and
big two dollar words that are banning
about i think it's great
my experience in um this empathy circle
technology we've had for the last month
has been really interesting because
sometimes um some of these super high
intellect guys
they're just not being heard or not
connecting and they're they're feeling
that absence
of like community toss and so i'm seeing
a bit of like
sprouting there of like maybe i need to
restructure
how i show up so i can actually connect
with people
and not just display my intellect so
that's been interesting and then um as i
was able to
sort of onboard and and be messy
and sort of express myself and make
statements
now i'm finding my empathetic role much
more delicious
and i really have this capacity to
listen and mirror back
and it's not as interesting to me to
like state my
claim but more to reflect and
and i see this uh this change in people
as they feel heard
like they're just enter a new space to
maybe they're more receptive and maybe
they have more of a vision of what it is
to embody
what they're feeling so um in fact
speaking of messi i feel like the
statement might even be a little bit
messy but
so far the empathy circles where we
really hunkered out and mirror each
other
has been the most fruitful you know
quote technology i've seen
but i'm also really inspired by you too
and and to hear you
say thank you daddy to peter oh my god
all right all right game game the [ __ ]
on
okay because i got that [ __ ] in space
i've been i've been toning it down
i've been toning myself way way way way
down honey
like these are the social terms that we
were saying it's invisible that we need
to get rid of
not for everyone cool ones for the cool
kids
awesome i love it so i think i think
that's it i think i've said enough thank
you
thank you dog daddy was about to mute
you there
emmanuel because i think that
um so uh let's do a christian
christian europe up next
okay i think my first question has been
answered pretty well already
is it okay if i ask my most recent
question here
yeah whatever whatever one is alive
thanks um
the question is on ideas about how to
harness the energy of social media
toward sense making and uh embodiment
and all of these things we like to talk
about
rather than strictly characterizing it
as the you know the dilemma of social
media
how you can tap in to the energy of
people wanting to engage with
liking and all the kind of more shallow
aspects of social media
uh toward you know something that you
believe in
beyond just the memes
does that question come across
you guys are muted by the way
how to harness the power of social media
in a way that's not
shallow yeah yeah or toward you know
whatever you
feel like you the change you want to see
um well this is something that i've
personally been thinking
of for a long time
and it's
challenging but also i feel it has a
very
high impact um possibility the
challenging part is that social media is
not a neutral space
which is like plugging and kind of like
fully with yourself like unlimited like
social media
is any social media any platform that
you go
has very strong um
not just but a very strong architecture
that's
that likes it kind of directs the
conversation
and directs your role in it towards a
certain place
and these places at least unfortunately
how everything is set up
don't tend to be the best places and the
places that feel like motion narrative
that's why i say challenging however
it's not impossible and if this if this
is done properly
it has and it has the potential for
having enormous impact
right now um at least
for what i've i've been yeah
thinking of and investigating i feel
like memes and influencers
are the two are the two things that
have been tried on social media that
already work
um and that could have a lot of
potential if done in our own way in like
the meta-modern way
and going back to that i feel that also
what the best way to play with this
is to get something that is already
working so um
same meme format or if you're doing like
influencer like say the same kind of
makeup tour how sore but like make it
meta modern because that's how you link
something from the previous imaginary
that's how you think something that
people have already an emotional
connection to and people already
understand
with something new and that's how they
can see the contrast
for me what at least it doesn't
necessarily
work so well um but this is all of
course
a matter of scale if you just do like
explainer videos
or if you just do um like podcasts or
interviews
this works so well for like a certain
audience
but for what what you need for like
broad culture
um change and like for broader scale
is a more subtle way of of
doing that content but it would this is
an area that definitely has a lot of
potential and
any agency that was exploring that with
these like specific lands
i think would be very promising and it's
something that yeah
we're definitely like putting our focus
in right now
still trying to figure it out does that
answer your question
yeah sure i look forward to seeing what
you guys figure out
yeah probably like ask us again in a
year yeah
tyler had a really good thought um i was
hoping you could share it tyler uh it
resonates a lot with
kind of what i'm doing with the journals
as well
sure can you all hear me okay
great um yeah i just want to say thanks
so much tarnelly really appreciated this
i was looking forward to it
i guess my comment was that in my brief
experience in this space
i noticed that these hyper jargony sense
maker figureheads
tend to stray away from telling any sort
of personal stories or personal
histories
when they're broadcasting unless they're
actually asked by some sort of moderator
whereas the more accessible types and
female broadcasters tend to often lead
with that
as you two did today actually um
and i find personally that hearing
people's personal stories and their
personal history
as well as in the moment displays a
vulnerability just immediately allows me
to connect and have a greater sense of
trust in the space that we're in
and it's something that i've learned
mainly through like the political
organizing space where
the work that i do around climate
justice the
the strategies we use are really tied to
telling stories as a way to connect with
folks
and so just kind of probing at how can
we create more spaces
for the folks on these sorts of calls to
be sharing stories as well as
the people that we're trying to learn
from
so not really a question but just a
suggestion idea for us all to consider
yeah yeah it's interesting and
the um the pointing out that we let
we led with that because yeah i mean it
just came naturally to
to introduce ourselves and i think
um when i think the reason why we did
that actually was because we felt
like we weren't going to be taken
seriously
so we just thought we have to just show
up with all of our cards and saying this
is who we are
and and you know we don't have the
the kind of cultural capital in the in
the sense-making scene that other people
have
um and and yeah and like you said you
connected to it and so that's really
actually at the beginning we were a bit
resistant of whether to do it or not to
do it because
it's true you said that most people
don't do it and then it felt
oh if we go and like talk about our
story
we will make it feel like everything is
about ourselves and we're trying to kind
of like
capitalize on our like young you know
like woman
thing and it will feel like an authentic
um
but then actually like the most
authentic thing is to just be yourself
and create a different space for you and
like personally when i read interviews
and when i like listen to podcasts
i really want to know the story like i
want to know the gossip like who are you
married to like what you know
what did you do when you were young like
and this is
not just the way of i think this is
really beautiful because you get to like
see the person not just that's what they
say
but as a full human being with all their
complexity and like
all you know their queries and their
story behind um and that's like great
for illustrating but also in like a more
strategic
way we are humans that are
wired to love gossip like information
and information about people
is power and like that was especially
true you know back in our hunter
gathering days
so even if you're just like talking
about stories in a very strategic how to
get more people hooked
that's just um a great idea but also it
just feels
much more comfortable for us it helps to
just it helps to make yourself yeah
as well yeah just be there so yeah thank
you
yeah and that whole thing about kind of
storytelling too
uh like i worry that some of these
scenes just kind of instrumentalize
storytelling in order to like
manipulate get things but it's something
like um what i see
you're doing and what i try to do in my
journals just kind of like allow
yourself to be a little messy
and give you permission to [ __ ] up and
be human and vulnerable and all that
stuff and
that a lot of people vibe with that yeah
totally we love the year
yeah i love it and it makes me feel like
much more human and approachable
yeah instead of like this host that has
you know like
it's creating like the empire of
intellectuals on the internet
we get to see you as like your true
like vulnerable like unhinged self and
that's really beautiful
and someone just put in the chat love
the reclaiming of gossip
so we we are at the hour um do you have
any uh
closing thoughts or anything you like to
leave us with
um i feel great about this on the way
here i said to any like what would at
the end of this
call like what would you have to feel to
feel like this went well
and uh i feel like it takes all my boxes
so
um i wanted to feel a sense of being
embodied throughout the conversation and
be able to keep it
keep a hold on on that grounding so yeah
absolutely i was thinking the same thing
like we're just having this like really
beautiful walk
um across you know where we live in
berlin and it was autumn i was like wow
how this will go i hope it goes
well and it just it yeah i felt like it
really went well i feel very grateful
to have been here and for now to open
this space
open the space and that our thoughts
resonated with all of you and not just
like our thoughts but our
vibe um that's what feels like most
comforting yeah
more the back than the thoughts um yes i
feel like that's that's like the most
surprised
exactly and yeah i guess um like
shameless self promo if you're curious
about like
experimenting like metamodern social
media and all this stuff
follow us because we're yeah we're not
showing you projects soon and we're
very excited to bring the conversation
in that way so yeah
beautiful yeah and just send me any
information you want i'll put it on the
kind of the description on the youtube
when i throw it up there
um i'll make some closing announcements
in a moment but tara and ellie thanks so
much uh
i really like was vibing with what you
were bringing and i
imagine a lot of people were here as
well um and hope you can bring more of
your vibe to the store and other places
in this scene
um so yeah if you want to continue this
conversation you can go to discord
we have a discord uh check out more
events uh
we gotta like maybe let's not what's
uh we got a party coming up um soon
uh let me let me share my screen
actually so i can properly show it off
uh boom
yes it is maybe not the end of the world
election party
uh stoic breath uh you know joe
uh is going to be there from human
systems
uh collective presence saying shame
breakthrough boot camp existential dance
party
that's dope if you haven't been to that
before so credit speed dating so if you
have vibe
with these playfully pretentious terms
uh feel free to go november 3rd
it's all day so i'm quite excited about
that
and uh yeah just check out the website
we have patreon at substack
um so that being said thank you so much
for coming
everyone thank you hi i wanna read